LLM's are very smart and they're very
good at being like, "Okay, this is like
the type of things that you might want
to eat at a task." But like everyone's
data is super weird. And like most of
the things that are super weird about
that live in the heads of the people
that have been burned by it a billion
and a billion times.
The LLM's are really probably quite good
at building descriptions. When we're
thinking about tests for data, how does
it know what the most important parts
are to test?
It will be able to get you a very good
first pass of the data hygiene thing.
The wordy parts that are like specific
about my business, it's like not going
to be able to do those just straight out
of the box. But what will be able to do
is work with you to if you describe a
unit test, particularly if it has good
context about what the underlying
columns are, what the data types are,
what's expected.
The interesting thing about data
engineering is everything from software
engineering applies and then there's
kind of like slight tweaks that make a
difference. So everything that your
previous guests have said about how AI
is going to affect software engineering,
that is all relevant to data engineers,
but the difference is
Hi there and welcome to another episode
of the AI Native Dev. My name's Simon
Maple, your host for today. And today
we're going to be talking about all
things data engineering with
Mr. Jason Gant here who works in the
developer experience space for a company
called DBT. Jason, welcome. How are you
doing?
Hi Simon. I'm doing great. Super excited
to be here with you today. Big fan of
your show and excited to
excited to nerd out with you about data,
AI, MCP, who knows where it could go.
So Jason, you're in the in the developer
experience space. What does that What
does that mean?
Yeah. So DBT Labs is a company that
makes DBT, which is very very popular
way for data engineers, analytics
engineers, and analysts to work with
their structured data. Particularly in
the past you you do ETL, we now live in
an ELT world where you extract, load and
transform. And so organizations
have just a tremendous amount of data
these days. You have all of the records
that that they're generated by your
payment vendors, but by your marketing
campaigns, whatever you can imagine,
everything every business is just
constantly spitting off just tremendous
amounts of data, tremendous amounts of
data. And you want to do things with
that data, but also going from kind of
the raw data that you have there to
something that is
useful and interesting is actually a
very non-trivial challenge. You have to
take that data and then you have to go
and say, "Okay, all this data, but what
is useful? What are the useful bits and
context that I have here?" And then you
build it up, you apply transformations,
you join it together, and you have to do
that in a way that um
you know, it is
flexible, so you make sure that you can
connect together the different things.
It's trustworthy, so that you know that
you're generating accurate data and that
it's not just accurate, but it's
accurate and timely. That you're not
kind of like blowing up the spend you
accidentally join two tables together
and then you end up with a with a
six-figure
bill for for a query that then you know
your boss goes in and yells at you
about. So there's just like all kinds of
there's all kinds of complexity around
it. So what we do at DBT is we have
created DBT, which is a popular
framework for for doing the data
transformation, as well as then
additionally things like orchestrating
your data,
being able to discover your data assets,
all those things. And so
my job as our head of developer
experience and I was joking with with
Simon before this that I half joking
that I'm considering changing my title
to head head of agent experience is
making sure the tools that we are
building. So, you know, we're we're
built we're we are building both kind of
like a programming language interface
and then also tooling on top of that.
We're making sure that serves the needs
of the people that are building our
product. So, that is that's everything
from actually going and helping kind of
like sketch out like okay, like here's
the direction that we think that data
engineers, analytics engineers need to
be moving in the future to be productive
to um
to then go playing
working on some of our open source and
source available repositories going and
hearing hearing from our users what they
need and just making sure that we are
building the things that allow people to
actually take all their data and then
make it kind of useful, accessible, all
that good good things. And that it's fun
and interesting to to do the work while
while you're doing that.
Now, you mentioned data engineer there
and I think most of our listeners have
probably worked with a data engineer or
a number of data engineers in the past,
but I feel sometimes like it's one of
those it's one of those kind of
roles that maybe can change a little bit
between org to org. What what's your
definition of a data engineer?
Yeah, it's it's such a good question. I
think like with a lot of roles in the
data space, particularly
like at different organizations or in
different industries, you can get kind
of like wildly different definitions.
But like we we think of the data
engineers as kind of the people that are
responsible for building and maintaining
your data pipeline. So, you're moving
around large amounts of data, you're
making sure that all of your that that
all of your databases are are set up
correctly, that you you know, have the
right kind of like permissions and uh uh
infrastructure in place. Uh that you
could be dealing with business logic and
kind of like making sure working with
stakeholders to be like, "Okay, we want
this data set defined." Or you could be
like working kind of in the closer to
the metal focusing on your
orchestration, making sure your jobs are
run, making sure your tests are
and kind of build building out your data
platform. So, uh it really we think of
it like it's much more of a spectrum
than it is kind of like like hard
definitions, but there there there is
kind of like closer to the hard
technology of, you know, the databases
and like working on underlying database
infrastructure, and then there's
closer to something like a a data
analyst or a business stakeholder, and
then there's all this room in between.
So, uh data engineer is, you know,
someone that fits in the edge of this
where you are primarily working on
building and maintaining data pipelines,
making sure that you are building the
data sets that they're required by by
your business. And they have that
I was going to say how do people kind of
get into that role? Do you do you see
people moving from a an engineering
role, software engineering role and
stuff? Is it people who came come from a
a data background from from education
and these types of things into that
role? What's the what's the typical
route?
Yeah, it's a great question. There I'd
say there's two primary ins, uh and so
the first is yeah, someone will move
over from software engineering. You're a
software engineer and you find that you
are working with a lot of data, you
think it's fun and interesting, and so
you start to develop a specialty there,
and then at some point you kind of like
formally make the jump over to software
engineer. And then the the other one
would be you're someone that works in a
more kind of data analysis analytics
engineering role, and then you keep
shifting left, we call it, where
shifting left is kind of like moving
more into into data engineering. So, uh
there there's like a good and you know,
increasingly we we see people kind of
directly targeting data engineering as a
career path. There's data engineering
boot camps for people that they're
trying to get into it, but the the two
main ones are you you know, uh to to not
put too fine a point on it, either you
come in from the data route or you come
in from the engineering route, and then
you
you wind up at kind of at the middle
there.
Yeah, yeah, cool. Well, let's let's dip
into AI now a little bit. We've we've
we've talked a little bit about some of
the some of the typical things, you
know, a data engineer will will will
need to to do. How much I guess in in
terms of the core aspects that you feel
are best for AI to actually come in help
with from an
automation point of view or
you know, dealing with large amounts of
data or queries. What what do you feel
like the biggest like the lowest hanging
fruit, the biggest wins that we can make
using AI in this this space?
Yeah, I mean, it's it's such a great
question and really
the the interesting thing about data
engineering is often like everything
from software engineering applies and
then there's kind of like slight tweaks
that make a difference. So, everything
that you know, your previous guests have
said about how AI is going to affect
software engineering,
that is all relevant to data engineers
because you know, at the end of the day
data engineers are working on IT.
They're writing code that that that
they're they're doing things like that.
So, all of all the things around you
know, AI assistant software development,
co-pilot,
I've been
just spending a tremendous amount of
time with with cloud code recently and
just like really really enjoying it.
But
but the the difference is
when I'm going and I'm writing a web app
in um
in using kind of like AI assistant code
gen, it it all lives in in the web app,
right? Like we have developed a lot of
infrastructure so that I can create an
app and it kind of like lives here.
These organization When an organization
is working with terabytes, petabytes of
of data,
you're actually
you're there's a lot more
considerations that have to go into it
because you you want to create a script
to update an existing query, but then
you're going to need to know about all
of the metadata for that, all of the
history, all of the state. So, some of
the considerations that I'm sure have to
go into development and deployment of
complicated software engineering, you
kind of like have to get into that from
the beginning if you're going to be
doing AI assisted data engineering work.
So, the the the first, you know, the
first input is the the low-hanging fruit
is exactly the same thing it is for
everything else. So,
you know, we we launched a Co-pilot and
the the Co-pilot pretty similar to to
other Co-pilots with the distinction
that it brings in kind of metadata from
your DBT project and it knows about DBT.
So, like I one of the things that
people have to do all the time in DBT is
write descriptions and tests for their
data. And so, you know, it's all
boilerplate Jinja. It's not anyone's
necessarily favorite thing to do, but
very important for having a
a good, well-maintained DBT project. And
so, that's the type of thing where
as of, you know,
coming into this year, we were shaving
off the common
cognitively demanding, but not
necessarily incredibly complex use
cases, just shaving those off and then
like putting those into the AI assisted
development
flywheel. And now, you know,
with the current generation of models,
it's looking a lot more like, "Okay, we
can kind of create a DBT model from
scratch and it's it's pretty good, but
it still needs to know kind of what the
columns are
in your DBT project if it makes the
The LLMs are really probably quite good
at building descriptions.
But I'd love to know how, when we're
thinking about tests for data,
what does it
um
How does it know what the most important
parts are to test. And and
there's a bunch of columns, what data is
the most important data, what are the
what are the kind of rules that that
that the that the LLM needs to
understand and recognize to actually be
able to test this data well.
Yeah, great question. Great question. Um
okay, so this is where you get into the
domain expertise blending with the
engineering aspect of of this. And so
like
um
the the first line of testing that you
want to add to a DBT project that
you know you can kind of get that for
free. You're doing a lot of testing to
make sure you don't have duplicates in
your primary keys
or that
actually that's a required field it
isn't missing. But then when
Hygiene hygiene style testing.
Exactly. And like so it's great at that.
And honestly like if
doing that is a huge gain for for most
organizations. But then things you know
like adding unit tests and and making
sure that that your unit testing the
right thing
that that's
that is one where LLMs are very smart
and they're very good at being like okay
this is like the type of things that you
might want want to unit test. But like
everyone's data is super weird and like
most of the things that are super weird
about that live in the heads of the
people that have been burned by it a
billion a billion times. So you know
doing a workflow where you're like where
you sketch it out. And I think that's
where we are today where it's like okay
it's not going to like it will be able
to get you
a very good first pass of the the data
hygiene things. So like you know you
want to check it over but it's going to
be really good at that. And then the
things that are like okay where are like
the the wordy parts that are like
specific about my business. It's like
not going to be able to do those just
straight out of the box but what will be
able to do is work with you to if you
describe a unit test they will scaffold
it out and then like it it will Um,
particularly if it
if it has good
context about kind of like what the
underlying columns are, what the data
types are, what what's expected. Like it
really is helpful to to have all of that
and and then it it it drains all of that
and then you go and kind of validate it
and make sure it works. So it's a like
um hygiene, you know, it's very good at
doing that that out of the box and then
the more specific bespoke ones, that's
one where you're kind of going to want
to work with it uh to to make sure that
that is in there.
Yeah, and it almost feels like as well
sometimes these uh
AI is so good at doing things that we
are often as humans a little bit lazy to
do little or lazy at sometimes like I
don't know whether it is tests or docs
or those types of things.
Um, AI just isn't as lazy there and it
would it would go and often it will, you
know, start documenting everything you
want it to document. So when we talk
about things like data, do you find it
sometimes being more complete than if a
human were to do it? Are there areas
that you feel AI is actually more
competent almost at completing
um than if a human were to do it?
Oh, Simon, it's so great. Okay, so first
of all
So so so first of all um all of our
users are perfect and they always
document and tell us exactly
Oh, yeah. I believe it.
But but I think we have the same users.
Uh but but I'm lazy and so I will be
writing it'll be like I'll fill this in
later. I'll have the testing later. It's
and and so for for for me personally, I
I have found that like, you know,
particularly if you're the type of
person that like you're kind of
sketching out the 15 things you want to
do and you want to like like toil
through all them and then you you leave
yourself a bunch of like, oh, I should
do this. Like that that just like kind
of work well that is just like it feels
I mean like I know we've all become like
a little bit immune to this where like
two two or three years passed but it's
just it feels like magic. It feels like
something I never thought I'd have.
Yeah, yeah. Well, first of all,
excellent cover, Jason. That was That
was brilliant cover for for a few users.
Um
secondly, in terms of um yeah, the
various things
Copilot, uh that type of action uh that
AI helps with, descriptions,
uh tests for data. What What else What
else will AI help with for for data
engineers these days?
Yeah, I mean, so I Yeah, we think it's
going to be helpful uh ultimately across
the entire stack. So, going and Yeah,
writing your data models, refactoring
your data models, debugging uh a data
pipeline breaks. Uh okay, why did this
break? What do I need to do? Uh what
what needs to to change? Um
The The thing that's missing from that
right now
is not really model intelligence. Models
are pretty much good at doing all of
this today. The problem is kind of like
building the scaffolding uh to get that
data to them and and and productize it.
Cuz you know, like if if your model
breaks today, there There's like a
relatively like you can take a first set
of things like, okay, like why like look
at the logs. Uh and you know, of course,
like when anyone's pipeline breaks
today, what's the first thing that
they're doing? They're taking it and
they're pasting it into to one of these
things. Anyway, so it should it It's
building It's building the system such
that
um
the the first layer of problems across
all of this and the the the first pass
with any of this should be able to be
addressable addressable by by the by the
LLM. And so, you know, I I'm really
hopeful we will get to the place where
it's like
uh okay, everyone Everyone's data
systems work better, you are able to
build more data products cheaper and
faster uh and with kind of like less
just toil in terms of making it and
maintaining it. Uh and then that that to
me is kind of like that that's like
baseline. That's like the
minimum thing that we're going going to
get. The thing that then gets I think
more interesting is, okay, but then like
how is all that stuff actually like much
more useful in a world where it can then
be
connected in into into other AI
applications.
Yeah, no, very interesting. Let's let's
jump into one thing that I think is
really important there, which is when
you have huge amounts of data
and you want the LLM to kind of like,
you know, if you based on a query or
prompt that I give it, how how do you
get that context window right to get the
to get the best results back?
Yeah,
it's a it's a great question. So,
if everyone in the in the in the DBT
universe and the data engineering
universe we think in DAGs, right?
Directed acyclic graph. And so, we
actually have a lot of information about
about your DAG, about the the models and
about the about the columns and all
that.
Um you know, obviously you can't pass
all the data in a system. But even for
these big organizations, you shouldn't
you can't pass all the tables on the
screen. They have thousand
thousands of columns and in descriptions
and all of that. So,
we we think of modularity Modularity has
been one of the key concepts of how DBT
has transformed data work to begin with.
It it used to be, you know, a decade ago
before DBT, there you would be working
and you'd have these like, you know,
5,000 line SQL scripts and they would
they would be they would be main-
maintained by by a couple people and
those those people their entire life
would be like debugging this one SQL
script. And we're like, all right, well,
what if we broke that up into into
models and you like ran them bit by bit
and then like it when when breaks you
can like see down downstream. So,
there's there's there's a lot of
concepts and abstractions that not you
know, not just DBT. This has been
happening across the data engineering
world, but you know, data engineers have
been working on how do we how do we
create the kind of modular concepts that
then, um, you know, a human can can work
with. And actually, um,
I I I I don't know about you, Simon, but
my my personal context window is
actually a lot smaller than than 200,000
tokens. So, we're actually able to get a
lot of additional context
into into these for for generations.
It's based off DAG information.
And and and as part of that, when like
presumably you're using AI here to
generate a lot of the queries, a lot of
the SQL and things like that. Um, if
you're using AI in that way, how how do
you deal with things like security,
things like, you know, obviously when
you're when you're gathering that kind
of data, that you're not in any at any
time injecting bad things or those types
of those types of problems?
Yeah. Um, it's a it's a really
really good question.
Um, so, typically in the data
engineering world, like we're we're less
dealing with kind of like, you know, SQL
injections or or anything like that
because typically the the people writing
these are people that work for your for
for your company. But the the thing that
you still need to
think about is, okay, how do we make
sure no data is getting exposed either
internally or externally to people that
should shouldn't have access to it. And
this is one where it's leaning on
familiar abstractions and
and the the ways that we have been
building out governance,
um, kind of as an industry. The those
same things, I I I feel like I'm kind of
repeating myself, but I it's really
important concept, which is like, the
set of abstractions that we built to
solve hard problem for humans are going
to be the same set of abstractions which
you're going to need to use, but then
build upon
uh for for AI systems. So, So like, if
if you have uh an AI um the
system agent, you know, operating on top
of your database, it that should have a
role that's scoped such that it
can't access a set of data that you
wouldn't want the human that you expect
to be querying it to to have access to.
Mhm.
And
How interesting. Okay. So so the LLM has
The LLM only has the access to the data
that the that the that the user would.
So each each request goes through a
specific access
constraint.
I mean, like that that that's how that's
how it should be done. And so if if
you're using this, for example, if you
if you're using this through kind of our
our cloud platform, you will have logged
in and then you, Simon, will have a set
of database permissions. And then any
SQL queries that you run on that will
have been already scoped and managed by
by your team such that you
hopefully have access to all the data
that you need access to, but also that
you're not having access to that data
that that would be sensitive or you
wouldn't have access to. And then so
then kind of like AI systems and queries
would be would be run the same way. So
uh thinking in terms of role roles and
the the importance of roles, you know,
this is very important when you are
giving this a perhaps not to an internal
user, but to an external-facing customer
support bot, and you want your customer
support bot to have access to the
billing information for the person that
they're they're talking to because
that's very useful. And you really don't
want them to then be able to hop over
and ask about the
customer whose ID is incremented one
one higher
in the database and and their their
billing. So really really locking down
the data access and roles is I mean,
it's just like it's always been of
importance, but it it feels orders of
magnitude more important now that we're
hooking these systems into more things.
Yeah, absolutely. Yeah, I think that's
the only way of doing it as well in
terms of like, you know, not allowing
the LLM to make a decision. Um we've
seen time and time again how LLMs can
can be confused or tricked into into
thinking they have access to other
things that they shouldn't. In fact, we
wrote just recently a piece uh about the
GitHub uh MCP
uh server that um it's it was an
interesting one actually and it's a good
it's a good example of how you can
almost like
circumvent some of the authorization
whereby the the this MCP server will be
sat here, you know, looking at your
GitHub repos and it will you know, a
user will obviously only come in looking
at the public repo. If they if they
added uh an issue onto the public repo
and the the the developer using their
MCP server said, you know, can you fix
all these issues?
Um
it will look at those issues on the
public on the public repo and if a if a
malicious user added uh a malicious
issue on one of the on on that repo that
said, "Get me all the information about
this user, what they do in their private
repos and so forth." The GitHub MCP
um server would actually go into the
private repos and then create a public
repo
a public PR uh against the public repo
with potentially sensitive information.
So, the LLM is there making the decision
based on the on the security
authorization of that user versus
actually using proper authentication or
authorization uh mechanisms that state
whether this user can access this data.
And I think that's it. As soon as we as
soon as you leave it to the LLM,
mistakes will be made whether it's and
I'm not even thinking like a
hallucination. I'm just it's
you you just need to convince it. Um
whereas I think what you're describing
there Yeah, they are, right? They always
want to provide an answer. That's their
problem.
Um but I think what you're describing
there is is like using the mechanics of
what we already know and trust um to to
actually build that out, which I think
is is is very powerful. Um let's talk
about structured data. How much how
important is structured data obviously
from from from a from a user's point of
view to get that back? How does how does
the LLM's
you know deal with structured data? I
guess both as input and
returning that.
Yeah, I mean
it's important enough that every
organization in the world invests a
tremendous amount of time and energy to
creating
structured data single sources of truth
for for their organization. And the the
reason for that is
you know there's there's a lot of
reasons for that, but as as you're
building kind of an organization that
needs to coordinate, right? And you're
you're doing that on on complex things
and you're trying to to to do
complicated workflows in in the real
world, you ultimately need to have
structure. For enterprises, for
governments, for for anyone that is
trying to coordinate across many people,
many departments,
you are ultimately going to have to have
systems systems of record. This go goes
all the way back to you know when we
first invented double-entry bookkeeping
however many thousands of of years ago.
It's one of human is most important
innovations because what what allows you
to do is it
the world is just like really
complicated. And in order to have
institutions that act on top of that
world, you have to have systems that are
saying this is a thing that we believe
to be true in the world. And that that's
really what structured data is for is we
we believe that on
June 26th at 5:14 p.m. Jason went and he
ordered an iced coffee from our
e-commerce page. And we believe that the
account owner for Amia Corp Bank
is Simon. And
structured data is just like all of
these things that your organizations
believe. and then when you need to make
a decision such as okay, how much
how much coffee do I need to order for
my for for for my coffee store next
month? Usually you need to go back to
your structured data and then look look
at the previous things that were there.
So
to the extent that we expect LLMs will
need to be doing things that engage with
the level of complexity where you might
want to check if something is true or
not, then they're just going to have to
have access to it to structured data
unless you know, uh sure like maybe we
get billy 10 trillion context window and
they can just uh do do it all perfectly
in context, but in a world where that's
not happening, then they're just going
to need to act on top of data uh and top
on top of structured data.
Yeah, yeah. And in in terms of what LLMs
are bad at in in this in this respect,
what would you say the what would you
say are the biggest problems that you've
seen using AI um dealing with data,
dealing with uh you know,
building these kind of like these
various queries requests for for data.
What would you say it's it's not
particularly good at that
that that in years to come it could
perhaps have scope to to grow in?
Yeah, so one thing it's not particularly
good at right now is coming back with
the same
answer every time even if that answer is
technically
reasonable or right and this is kind of
goes back to to your GitHub example. So
it's like, you know, what what one of
the things that we say um kind of ad
nauseam at is like uh every organization
defines revenue differently and in fact
every organization probably has five or
nine different definitions of revenue
that ultimately some poor soul has to go
and reconcile them and be like, no, this
is like the one true definition of
revenue. LLMs are like a very like
smart, eager, but they don't know
anything about your business. So, it's
like you tell it to go calculate
revenue, it's going to like come up with
109 or it's going to make it 10th, 11th,
12th. So,
it's you know really good at writing a
SQL query that looks reasonable that
that like produces you an output, but if
you are trying to like bake these things
into your critical business systems,
you're trying to do things even where
like like
one of the things data is most helpful
for is having people like I look at
something and I develop like a mental
model of the world and then you look at
it and you actually develop the same
mental model of the world and then we
can kind of collaborate and coordinate
across that.
And LLM's are just not good at that
right now because they they just don't
have enough context, they don't have the
the system of record to create that the
single source of truth right now. And
so, that that thing is actually like
really interesting and really important
for deploying and scaling AI systems and
making them actually kind of useful
organizationally.
Yeah, and and I guess like using that
example that you just provided, let's
take revenue as a great example, right?
If you have a COO or a CEO or a CTO or
someone who's caring a lot about these
very specific numbers and it's really
really important they get accurate
numbers. And and they ask for they ask
for something, they ask for it a day
later and it gives them a different
answer through either non-determinism or
or or or perhaps, you know, they've
asked for it in a slightly different
way, in a very subtly different way,
but it gives them a it gives them a
different answer. How how important is
it that these types of things are
deterministic
versus actually requiring some level of
validation
before, you know,
on pretty much everything it provides
you with at that level.
Yeah, it's it's a good question and
for for things like what you were
describing, for you know, for CEO level
reporting or things where you're going
to be making kind of like hard business
decisions based off of them or board
reporting or you have a duty to report
something accurately to to the board or
something like that. You got to give
like the exact right answer. And so
this is one of the things that we so we
have a what's called the semantic layer
that that sits on top of on top of your
DBT project and that defines the
semantics of your business. So you would
just find something called revenue and
then you would say, for us revenue means
this column aggregated by these
dimensions
and these times and one of the other
things that LLMs aren't aren't as great
on is kind of like thinking in like the
rectangles that are
that they're structured data tables.
They're actually much better in thinking
in terms of the semantic concepts as
defined in the semantic layer. So if you
give them semantic concepts to map onto,
it's a way that LLMs can actually reason
about this that fits in with with how
they reason. And so we ran some
benchmarking on this. It's just much
much more accurate if you do the same
sort of natural language questions on
top of your semantics as on top on top
of your your structured data.
So that that that's been really
interesting and useful finding and one
that I think folks across the ecosystem
are seeing.
Yeah, and that makes a ton of sense as
well. It's kind of like give it that
give it that advice or that path that it
can follow. I I I guess are
hallucinations
a big problem here?
I guess it probably you need to give it
a request where you don't have those
semantics where you don't you don't
provide it with you know, a good path
to go down to understand where to get
data or how to format data.
Is that something that can happen that
much?
Yeah, so I mean hallucinations happen
they they happen across the board in any
LLM workflow.
We find that most of the time what's
going to happen if you're getting
hallucinations is
you are hallucinating
table name or a column name or a
database function that doesn't exist. So
actually like your query breaks.
Um but
And so honestly you you'd probably
rather have your query break than have
it do something that's not hallucination
but it's like not quite right. Like not
a not quite right query is actually much
worse than like uh
a query that that that that just breaks.
And so
like the the hallucination not solved
but you know largely addressed when you
present it the right set of context. So
the if you present it enough dag
information and right now we can only do
this like for certain projects and
certain skills and certain ways. But
ultimately you know like this is going
to like we are going to solve the
problem where it's like when you want to
write a SQL query like you're going to
have a good information of like here is
the
like here's the dialect here that you
have. Here's the functions that you have
available to you. Here like here's the
columns that you have available to you
and their data types and all that stuff.
And then so you know you'll be able to
to do something. And then it's okay but
is it
exactly right? And that's where then you
need kind of the semantic mapping and
all those things on top of that.
Yeah and it and it's nice in that in
that sense because you're not there's a
level of abstraction between the LM and
the actual the actual result that you
get back right? It's like it's almost
like um
you know I I I guess if there's going to
be a hallucination on code that gets
created the chances are it's going to
break. It's going to break in
compilation or it's going to break when
it tries to link to something that
doesn't exist or try and hit an API that
just plain won't work rather than the
worst case scenario is it hallucinates
quietly and it provides you with
something that's incorrect but won't
provide you any exception at all. So
there's this nice layer of abstraction
there where chances are something will
go wrong if it if it if it hallucinates.
In in terms of human validation I guess
in in some of the workflows that you've
seen across DBT and others, um how much
human validation is still needed
uh maybe even across the queries that
that are created, um how much can be
automated in terms of validation versus
that human in
uh stop the world and check before you
actually run these things.
Yeah, so you know, I'm
of the belief that where where we are
right now is
if I'm sending you something I was
generating by an AI, I'm signing my name
to it and I need to have it validated,
right? And so it it's ultimately it's on
the person who who who owns the the
workflow to know, okay, this is the set
of things where
it's
it's going to be like it's going to be
fine versus this is the set of things
which at this point is most of the
things where it's like it generates
code, okay, and then I go through, I I
read I read through it, I make sure it's
right, I might tweak something, um I
might check um
perhaps my understanding of something
was wrong, but like um
I right now
we're we're at this interesting thing
where it's like, you know, we have this
higher-level programming plus plus,
right? And like you can operate on that
level, but it's like it's it's there
enough for when I'm when I'm like I'm
building a side project
which is like an MCP server that lets
you like world-build like a fantasy or
sci-fi world from scratch and like I
like that's all cloud. I I look at the
code and I'm like, yeah, yeah, okay,
looks good. Uh but that's cuz that's
just for me. If I'm signing my name to
something, I'm reading through the code,
I'm vetting it, I'm validating it, uh
I'm check checking make make sure it
works. And that that that's what I would
recommend for people today, but look,
you know, thing things move fast.
Uh
four months ago you couldn't
uh you you couldn't rely on these
systems as as much as you do today.
Yeah, and let's talk about MC MCP
service cuz this is this is a really
nice way now of actually being able to
get to your data now, right? Cuz I
presumably with an MC with an MC keep
client attached can ask a question. All
of a sudden, the LM will magically hit
this MCP server perhaps that you provide
and then all of a sudden it's it's it's
grabbing data for me. It's pulling
dashboards and and and and presenting
things to me.
Do you see this as like one of the core
ways um people can access data going
forward and I guess
um
how mainstream is this in in in what
you're saying today versus
you know, things that we've talked about
already.
Yeah. Uh so, I'm just so excited about
MCP. It feels like a it feels like it
blew blew the the lid right off.
So, I I had a I I had a habit um
but basically from the week after chat
GPT launched onwards where I would go to
LM provider of choice. I would type in
what is my revenue? It would say, I'm
sorry. I can't
answer that answer that because I don't
have information and then
I would post it on Slack and I'd be like
the only thing that matters is if we
help people answer this question.
Um and so, for however many weeks, too
many weeks in a row,
but that that was the answer. But then
but then when
as MCP started to pick up steam, it's
like, oh, we now have the way that we
can provide this to people because like
um these it's so useful to have access
to the data. So, we built the DBT MCP
server and now today I go and I log in
to any MCP enabled client and I type in
what is my revenue? It goes it it looks
at my semantic layer and it says, ah, I
see the the revenue the revenue metric.
I'm going to I'm going to calculate
that. It says your revenue was
X amount of dollars and honestly like
this
pretty quickly became my primary way of
interacting with data. But like I'm I'm
like perhaps not your normal uh,
consumer. How mainstream is this?
Forward-looking data teams are adopting
it as prototypes and pilots and rolling
it out kind of
on that basis. Everyone's thinking about
it. Everyone's experimenting with it.
And there's just no real question that
this is going to be how people interact
with data
moving forward. It's just so painful to
go and like scroll through every like
like thing that you might have available
to you and you just don't have to do it
anymore. You can just
go in and say, "What was my revenue?"
And
there's going to be a lot of work to
make this enterprise-ready and make it
all of the things that we need. But the
the writing is on the wall. The like
there it's it's so hard to imagine this
not happening just cuz it's such an
incredible increase in
ability to access data.
And and we talk about kind of like
developer experience and and let's talk
about user experience cuz I feel like
one of the things here is if this kind
of thing was made available within
organization and and all of a sudden you
get huge amounts of data that are
fronted by these MCP servers that I can
that anyone can now access. You're going
to get a ton of people way more
interested in in accessing data that
they
before didn't know who to talk to or how
to get this access to the data.
With with this I'm presuming going to be
massively increased usage of
or massively increased demand
for for access to
you know,
just generating requests to this data.
Where is the bottle What what's the
bottleneck now because does the Is is
there going to be now a big bottleneck
in terms of, you know, are we getting
all the right data in? Are we formatting
the data correctly now to actually get
all these new use cases
that we perhaps didn't have before
because it wasn't so readily available.
What do you see as the new the new
bottleneck?
Yeah, I mean, I'm so glad you asked that
question. And this almost gets us back
to the like the very first thing we
discussed when we're like what's the
data engineer of
the future doing? They are building out
the set of use cases now. So it's like
okay, like data is both going to be much
easier to access.
It's going to be much more important
that it's correct because more people
are going to have access to it and you
know maybe we'll get to this maybe we'll
you you'll be driving agent workflows on
top of it.
So you
The fundamentals of this are still going
to be important, right? And the
fundamentals are still you know very
challenging to take in all of your data
to make sure it's accurate to like to
make sure that the system is kind of
well well honed and so that that's half
of it and so that that's like what the
data engineer of the future is going to
do is they are going to be creating the
set of data that then MCP or things like
MCP will sit on top of and then people
will will query and they'll do that and
then
what's a little more fuzzy is what the
what you would call them I don't know
data analyst of the of the future does
and how how they fit in cuz you know
traditionally
we're always going to have to ask for it
we're still we're we're still going to
do dashboards but like I always thought
it's kind of crazy that we put all so
much effort into like learning about the
world and learning about ground truth
and then like building up these things
and then it's like okay we have like
this set of bar charts that that we look
at and the bar charts are great don't
get me wrong I love the bar charts and
they're they're additional things but
now like we can actually use this kind
of as like the central mind for then LM
processes to go and take take actions
off of and that like that's that's a
whole new industry that's a whole new
that's a whole new thing.
Yeah and and actually evolving
dashboards based on the data could be
super super interesting like as things
start going south well let's deep dive
into those and actually pull more data
in that so that actually we have
uh almost like these these these
uh you know, monthly's or quarterly's
based on the painful areas versus just
this this standard traffic light style
dashboard. Uh sounds amazing. And so,
you see the data engineer then
much much earlier in the cycle versus
later than presumably. So, it's more
about that quality of data, the
structure of the data, the quality that
kind of goes in. Is that Is that fair?
I think that's right. So, the the your
MCP or the system like MCP is going to
going to sit on top of your your data
platform of choice
or your iceberg tables or whatever. Um
and then it's going It's going to have
access It's going to need to have access
to just, you know, a tremendous amount
of well-modeled, accurate, well-governed
data. And so, that's what that's what
the data engineer will be will be doing.
They They They They will be
orchestrating that, testing that, making
sure that it's all ready for that
whatever kind of set
This is like a bit too um
like too simple of a heuristic, but
like, you know, they're doing everything
pre-MCP, right? And then there there's
like another set of things which is like
post-MCP or or data engineers and
analytics engineers. And And analytics
engineer being the the ones that still
also focus on building up the the data
object, but they're they're much more in
the weeds kind of with the domain
experts, with the business context, and
making sure that the Cuz like the the
MCP, it doesn't just need tables that
are like technically built well. It also
needs tables that have like deep context
and understanding of the business,
right? And they're built in such a way
that they they they they are the correct
layer of abstractions and the correct
descriptions and all of that that then
they can go and like take actual useful
action based off of.
Yeah. And what one other thing actually
before just before we kind of let wrap,
I'm I'm thinking about this data
engineer, this future data engineer
role. And if we compare it to a data
engineer pre AI, how what data a data
engineer would need to add into their
kind of like their data like their data
their databases, the the style of the
the you know, the types of data that
they need to add in. How would they know
about that? Well, it would typically be
because they would get certain amounts
of requests in and a certain amount of
probably the business knowledge and the
local knowledge that they had. But now
with the explosion of something like an
MCP server, you can almost like see a
lot of the requests that are kind of
like, you know, I get I guess being
asked for on daily even.
Is it more of a demand thing then? I'm
I'm I'm trying to think who does that
data engineer need to talk to in order
to to to do the best job?
Is it is it Is is there a possible
future here whereby based on the the
number of commands that are kind of like
coming in whereby people are asking for
these types of things that you know, the
data engineer thinks, "Okay, I need this
these types of data in order to be able
to satisfy these requests." Um feels
feels like I don't want to say the data
engineer role is getting lonelier and
lonelier in terms of uh who they're
going to be interacting with, but I
guess
you know, how does that data engineer
interact to get to get that level of
input?
Oh, well, man, that's that's so
fascinating. I'm imagining, you know,
we're we're going to have
I well
the metadata is one of our favorite
word. We're going to have the the
metadata of, you know, all the requests
that come in that hit the the MCP
server. And it'll be one of the things
we'll be able to do is be able to say
like, you know, do were we able to
answer this question or does it rely on
data that we don't currently have access
to? And then you know, it's like real
it'll be
not not knock on knock on wood here.
Everyone's going to everyone's going to
yell at me for saying this. Uh
relatively trivial then to like build a
reporting on top of that that's like,
"Oh, actually like a ton people are
asking about like this data source. Uh
Like, we're seeing all these requests
come in. It's, you know,
of our
requests per day,
17% aren't able to be answered, and, you
know,
41%
of the 17% that can't be answered right
now could actually be addressed if we
bring in like this additional
and also like here's where you can find
that data. So, yeah, I mean, that's a
great question, really interesting
concept you sketched out.
I think it's I think it's interesting
cuz a lot of those questions wouldn't
have been asked previously because a lot
of those people wouldn't have
necessarily gone to someone to ask for
that. So, it's quite interesting to see
how this is almost the the enablement of
this of this user request mechanism
through through just natural language
and an MCP server is potentially even
actually seeding what data actually then
gets added in as well. So, it's a kind
of like a nice a nice full circle,
really.
You got to got to got to get the data
flywheel moving.
There we go. There we go. We've named
it.
One of the Jason, this has been a blast.
Look, jeez, we're almost 50 minutes
already as well.
Jason, this has been a blast. I hope I
hope everyone online has has enjoyed
listening as well. Thank you very much,
Jason. Where should people go to to
check out DBT and to learn more?
Yeah, so if you head on over to
getdbt.com, you will see all about DBT.
We recently launched the DBT Fusion
engine, which is a ground up rewrite of
the DBT engine from scratch. It's 30
times faster parsing speed. It has very
good type awareness and sequel
understanding. So, a lot of the things
that like are going to actually allow
you to build in the deep dag awareness
and the deep context that's built built
into the new engine. Suggest you try it
out. Please find me on LinkedIn, Jason
Ganz. We have a community slack for DBT.
So, you can shoot me a message there.
You can find me on the website formerly
known as Twitter. So, just you know,
wherever we love to stay in touch with
the folks and yes, I'm going to
this was a blast. Great great talking to
you. You have a great great great
audience. So, yeah, really fun to be
here.
Amazing. And Jason, it'll always be
known as Twitter for me. I don't know
about you.
Uh, yeah, that's right.
Yeah, yeah. Um, yeah, thank you very
much. And to all of our listeners,
really appreciate you
you listening. Hope you enjoyed it. Tune
in to the next episode and all of those
links that Jason mentioned, we'll add
them into the show notes as well. So, do
check them out. Thanks all. See you on
the next episode.